## Joel Worrall

717.385.9970 / joel@joelworrall.com / @tangollama

# Innovation, Strategic Leadership, Digital Transformation, Product & Brand Development, Executive Management

## Summary

I started my career in the software industry as a programmer, architect, and consultant. More than a decade ago, I began growing my skills in the areas of people management, organizational leadership, strategic planning, brand development, product management, and enabling business transformation.

Today, I'm equipped with a service-oriented management philosophy, a strategic execution track record, and a passion for building great technology and great teams. My goal is to join a leadership team with a mission I can embrace, a culture I can influence, and a vision I can help shape.

#### Skills

- Technology product development, including hands-on software engineering and architecture
- Management of departments across distributed offices, time zones, and continents
- Team leadership, mentoring staff and subordinates, managing up, and coaching peers
- Brand and product positioning as well as internal and external messaging
- Marketing and fundraising, including proposal creation and presentation
- Strategic planning and execution with sustainable results
- Corporate culture leadership, embracing and setting pace for core values
- Personnel management, including restructuring organizational reporting relationships
- Talent identification, recruitment, and onboarding
- Volunteer recruitment and management, including open source software contributors
- Strong presentation, public speaking, and written communication skills
- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Multi-million dollar budget management
- Seven years of Board-level reporting experience
- Classroom management and curriculum creation in a higher education setting

## **Education & Training**

Bachelor's in Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA (2000) Master's in Religion, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA (2015) The Marketing Seminar with Seth Godin, <a href="https://themarketingseminar.com">https://themarketingseminar.com</a> (2017)

## Presentations & Talks

See videos of several of my public talks and presentations at <u>ioelworrall.com/talks</u>.

## Experience

#### Stripe (January 2021 to present)

In 2021, I joined the leadership team of the Stripe Developer Products organization. Our teams deliver the infrastructure, services, API's, education, and support systems that power all of Stripe's products.

#### New Relic (2.5+ years)

New Relic is the industry leader in monitoring the modern cloudstack, adding over two trillion events and metrics per day to their real-time analysis platform while serving over 17,000 customers (including more than half the Fortune 100). Operating at the intersection of product and go-to-market, my roles provided strategic leadership and execution, often resulting in open source code.

#### Senior Director, Open Source - October 2020 - January 2021

- Part of the executive product leadership team, reporting to the Chief Product Officer
- Lead the cross-team development of the platform's deployment and onboarding architecture
- Oversaw the open source program office

#### <u>Director, Open Source and Developer Advocacy</u> – October 2019 - October 2020

- Hybrid product manager / engineering manager / architect while (by choice) still writing code
- Served in a primary support role to the GM of Developer Ecosystem
- Responsible for our developer advocacy content, event strategy, and developer programs
- Drove the establishment of our open source program office, strategy, and GM roadmaps

#### <u>Director, Programmability</u> – May 2019 - October 2019

- Lead the New Relic Labs team within our Services organization
- Represent customer platform needs to the Product teams in Portland and Barcelona
- Support the GM of New Relic One regarding programmable feature definition

#### Principal Extensibility Architect - May 2018 to May 2019

- Built early-stage customer solutions using GraphQL, React, and cloud services
- Helped deliver, shape, and support New Relic's Developer Program
- Championed the goals of the founder/CEO with regards to platform programmability

Primary technologies / tools: React, Node.js, HTML/CSS/JS, GraphQL, New Relic, GitHub, AWS

## Masterworks (10 months)

Re-platformed a 30-year-old agency that was focused on serving faith-based organizations in the rescue and relief sectors. In my role, I helped to reengineer the agency while simultaneously bringing digital products to market.

#### Vice President, Chief Technologist - August 2017 to May 2018

- Created a data service to aggregate constituent data across a myriad of platforms and tools to create a unified understanding of donor response as well as automation models
- Reshaped technology and digital delivery processes to follow industry best practices
- Built the staffing capabilities of the agency with regards to technology and digital marketing
- Vetted and implementing outsourcing and partner relationships

• Led platform and partner selection for technology-related systems and solutions
Primary technologies / tools: Google BigQuery, Looker, Piwik Pro, React, Node.js, PHP, Symfony, MySQL,
HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Pantheon, WPEngine, Salesforce.com, Google Apps

#### Messiah College (2 years)

In my first, professional teaching engagement, I taught an introductory web technologies course in Spring 2018 followed by a two-semester senior capstone course in system analysis, design, and implementation. I've recently chosen to reduce my role to guest lecturer in Computer Science.

<u>Adjunct Instructor</u> - February 2018 to May 2019 <u>Guest Lecturer</u> - September 2019 to Present

#### CURE International (7.5 years)

Member of the executive leadership team, head of technology, marketing, and CURE's innovative online donor reporting platform (<u>CUREkids</u>), providing oversight and strategic direction to a global charitable healthcare organization with 1,600 employees and an operational presence in 29 countries.

<u>Chief Technology Officer and Office of the CEO</u> – June 2016 to May 2017 <u>Chief Technology Officer</u> – May 2014 to June 2016 <u>Vice President of Technology and Marketing</u> – July 2010 to May 2014 <u>Vice President of Technology</u> – October 2009 to July 2010

- Oversaw all technology, marketing, brand-building and creative efforts
- Served as the lead executive and primary communicator through a CEO transition
- Architected and co-founded the award-winning cure.org and the CUREkids platform
- Co-founded the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source software project
- Led transition from traditional nonprofit software tools to a full cloud technology strategy
- Wrote and spoke for conferences and events across a variety of audiences and venues
- Conducted executive recruiting and management
- Directed crisis communications and public relations
- Directed the creation of CURE's content marketing strategy
- Oversaw the growth of CURE's first, successful monthly recurring revenue program
- Led the messaging and execution for CURE's largest annual fundraising event (\$6M)

Primary technologies / tools: PHP, MySQL, jQuery, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Salesforce.com, Google Apps, Mailchimp, Stripe, Hubspot, DigitalOcean, Rackspace

## Mzinga & KnowledgePlanet Inc. (3.5 years)

Led a 75-person engineering department of a venture-backed enterprise software company. Responsible for technology roadmap, product development, acquisition due diligence, and R&D.

<u>Vice President, Engineering & Development</u> – March 2009 to October 2009

<u>Director of Engineering</u> – August 2008 to March 2009

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008

<u>Development Manager</u> – Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

<u>Software Architect</u> – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

• Led shift of product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete Software as a Service multi-tenant, single instance environment

joelworrall.com / LinkedIn / GitHub

- Provided technical leadership through a debt restructuring and recapitalization event
- Guided the engineering organization through the merger of three separate companies and development organizations as well as the incorporation of an offshore, outsourced team
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services
- Performed technical diligence through acquisitions
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships

Primary technologies / tools: Java, HTML/CSS/JS, Oracle, SVN, CVS, FogBugz

## (Volunteer) HospitalRun (4.5 years)

Co-founder of the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source health information platform, responsible for strategic direction, community management, messaging, code contributions, and reviewing pull requests.

<u>Core Team [Volunteer]</u> – February 2014 to July 2018

Primary technologies / tools: Node, Ember, CouchDB, PouchDB, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic

#### Java Brewery, Inc (3 years)

Outsourced system architecture, software development, and interim engineering management.

Sole Proprietor and Senior Consultant - April 2003 to June 2006

- Engaged in outsourced product development, management, market research, and leadership
- Served as technical liaison and interim engineer for multiple organizations
- Analysis of company models, architecture, requirements, design and implementation services
- Architected the content management tools for Comcast

Primary technologies / tools: Java, MySQL, Postgres, CVS, SVN

## CommNav Inc. (3 years)

Lead Java developer of a 20-person startup focused on a business portal framework.

<u>Lead Architect</u> – July 2000 to April 2003

## Knowledgeplanet Inc. (1 year)

Entry-level developer that quickly took over leadership in an existing and more senior team.

Software Engineer – May 1999 to June 2000